Finding Aid for the The Papers of James Hampton Kirkland
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
- Writings - Addresses
  - “College Ideals, Personal and Institutional”(2) At the Commencement of the University of Oklahoma, 6/4/1929 (Box 13, File 18)
  - “College Lessons to be Learned”, undated (Box 13, File 19)
  - “College Life”, undated (Box 13, File 20)
  - “College Life in Relation to Post Academic Life”, 5/13/1931 (Box 13, File 21)
  - “College Raises and Settles Questions”, undated (Box 13, File 22)
  - “Colleges and Newspapers in A Common Service” At the Newspaper Institute held at Macon, Georgia, 2/17/1928 (Box 13, File 23)
  - “Credits”, undated (Box 13, File 24)
  - “Culture outside Classroom”, undated (Box 13, File 25)
  - “Dr. S. A. Knapp’s Work”, undated (Box 13, File 26)
  - “Duty and Responsibility”, undated (Box 13, File 27)
  - “Education”, 4/9-11, 1926 (Box 13, File 28)
  - “Education and Commerce”, undated (Box 13, File 29)
  - “Education and Industry” At Tennessee Society of New York, 1/8/1921 (Box 13, File 30)
  - “Education and Scholarship” At the Fiftieth anniversary of University of Chattanooga, 4/25/1936 (Box 13, File 31)
  - “Entrance Requirements”, undated (Box 13, File 32)
  - “Exams -- II”, undated (Box 13, File 33)
  - “Financial Obligations”, undated (Box 13, File 34)
  - “First Impressions”, 10/5/1914 (Box 13, File 35)
  - “Freedom”, undated (Box 13, File 36)
  - “George Washington” (1) At a Celebration held in Montgomery, Alabama, 2/21/1932 (Box 13, File 37)
  - “George Washington” (2), 2/22/1932 (Box 13, File 38)
  - “Good Institutions vs. Conduct”, undated (Box 13, File 39)
  - “Grading”, undated (Box 13, File 40)
  - “Health”, undated (Box 13, File 41)
  - “Higher Education and the State” At University of Pennsylvania, 4/8/1921 (Box 13, File 42)
  - “Higher Education in the South” At the Inauguration of Dr. Bradford Knapp as President of Alabama Polytechnic Institute, Auburn, Alabama, 5/20/1929 (Box 13, File 43)
  - “Honor System”, undated (Box 13, File 44)
  - “Ideals in College and in Life” At University of Oklahoma, 6/4/1929 (Box 13, File 45)
  - “Industry”, undated (Box 13, File 46)
  - “Industry and Culture”(1) At the American Cotton Manufacture Association, 5/26/1922 (Box 13, File 47)
  - “Industry and Culture”(2) At the Convention Dinner of the Sons of American Revolution, 5/22/1923 (Box 13, File 48)
  - Introducing President Elliott (of Harvard), undated (Box 13, File 49)
  - Introducing Dr. Thorvald Madsen, at Vanderbilt University, 3/10/1937 (Box 13, File 50)
  - “Law and Courtesy”, undated (Box 13, File 51)
  - “Lessons”, undated (Box 13, File 52)
  - “The Liberal Arts College -- Ideals Changing and Development” At the celebration of the Seventy-fifth Anniversary of Wofford College, 10/18/1929 (Box 13, File 53)
  - “Lower Life and Higher”, undated (Box 13, File 54)
  - “Magnetawau”, 8/12/1919 (Box 13, File 55)
  - “Methodist Education”, undated (Box 13, File 56)
  - “Mr. McKeilly”, 5/13/1925 (Box 13, File 57)
  - “My Interest in Education”, 1/5/1900 (Box 13, File 58)
  - “My Relation with Dr. Purdue”, undated (Box 13, File 59)
  - “The Nature and Power of Vision” At Y.M.C.A., 2/8/1914 (Box 13, File 60)
  - “The Need and Making of Leaders” At the Meeting in Honor of Bishop Maxon, 10/18/1932 (Box 13, File 61)
  - “The New Day and a New World”, undated (Box 13, File 62)
  - “The New Year A Fiction”, undated (Box 13, File 63)
  - “Notes on the Bimillennium of Horace” A Round Table Lead, 10/3/1936 (Box 13, File 64)
  - “Obligations to Our City”, 10/24/1912 (Box 13, File 65)
  - “Old College Curriculum”, undated (Box 13, File 66)
  - “Open the Eyes of the Young Men”, undated (Box 13, File 67)
  - Opening Address at Vanderbilt University, 10/11/1896 (Box 13, File 68)
  - Opening Address at Vanderbilt University, 10/10/1897 (Box 13, File 69)
  - Opening Address at Vanderbilt University, 10/8/1899 (Box 13, File 70)
  - Opening Address at Vanderbilt University, 10/13/1901 (Box 13, File 71)
- Writings - Addresses
  - Opening Address at Vanderbilt University, 9/29/1920 (Box 14, File 1)
  - Opening Address at Vanderbilt University, 9/24/1924 (Box 14, File 2)
  - Opening Address at Vanderbilt University, 9/1928 (Box 14, File 3)
  - Opening Address at Vanderbilt University, undated (Box 14, File 4)
  - Opening Address at Vanderbilt University, undated (Box 14, File 5)
  - Opening Address at Vanderbilt University, undated (Box 14, File 6)
  - “Our Neighbors in Nashville” At the Inauguration of Thomas E. Jones as President of Fisk University, 12/17/1926 (Box 14, File 7)
  - “Patriotism and Service”, 1/8/1913 (Box 14, File 8)
  - “Peace and World Order” At the Religious Education Association, 2/27/1917 (Box 14, File 9)
  - “The Permanence of Scholastic Ideals” At University of Chicago, 3/17/1931 (Box 14, File 10)
  - “The Permanence of Scholastic Ideals” At University of Florida, 6/1/1931 (Box 14, File 11)
  - “Preparation”, undated (Box 14, File 12)
  - “Preparation vs. Execution” (V.U. Opening Address), 9/23/1936 (Box 14, File 13)
  - “Preparedness”, undated (Box 14, File 14)
  - “Prizes of Life”, undated (Box 14, File 15)
  - “Progress and Problems of Religious Education in the Southern States”, undated (Box 14, File 16)
  - “Progress in Higher Education Since 1787” At University of Pittsburgh, 2/28/1912 (Box 14, File 17)
  - “Purposeful Life”, undated (Box 14, File 18)
  - “Radio Talk to Vanderbilt Alumni”, 4/9/1926 (Box 14, File 19)
  - “Recreation: Social”, undated (Box 14, File 20)
  - “Religious Life in College”, undated (Box 14, File 21)
  - “Religious Progress”, undated (Box 14, File 22)
  - “Remarks of Chancellor James H. Kirkland, 40th Anniversary”, 7/12/1933 (Box 14, File 23)
  - “The Responsibility of the Faculty in the Development of Personality”, 3/9/1932 (Box 14, File 24)
  - At Meeting of Faculty Forum, Vanderbilt University (Box 14, File 24)
  - “Right View of College Life”, undated (Box 14, File 25)
  - “The Romance of Labrador” (A Round Table Lead), 1/5/1935 (Box 14, File 26)
  - “Routine Study”, undated (Box 14, File 27)
  - “Sense of Values”, 1/6/1926 (Box 14, File 28)
  - “Some New Year Reflections”, 1/17/1919 (Box 14, File 29)
  - “Some Problems of Southern Colleges” At Central College, undated (Box 14, File 30)
  - “Some Recent Development Educationally”, undated (Box 14, File 31)
  - “Some Special Items”, undated (Box 14, File 32)
  - “The Soul of America” At Washington and Lee University, 1/19/1918 (Box 14, File 33)
  - “The South”, undated (Box 14, File 34)
  - “South Campus”, undated (Box 14, File 35)
  - “The South -- Progress in Education”, undated (Box 14, File 36)
  - “Southern Education”, undated (Box 14, File 37)
  - “Southern Education and Southern Thought” At University of Pennsylvania, 2/27/1914 (Box 14, File 38)
  - “Sowing and Reaping”, 1/18/1912 (Box 14, File 39)
  - “Standards of Honor in College”, undated (Box 14, File 40)
  - “Statement for Dr. Robert L. Kelly”, 11/8/1934 (Box 14, File 41)
  - “A Statement at the Board of the Southern College Association, 7/9/1936 (Box 14, File 42)
  - “The Teacher and His Work”, 12/29/1908 (Box 14, File 43)
  - “Teacher in Constructive Statesmanship”, undated (Box 14, File 44)
  - “Things Worth Doing”, undated (Box 14, File 45)
  - “Tibet” For the Round Table, undated (Box 14, File 46)
  - “Trip from Stuart, Florida, to Nashville”, 2/24-25/1934 (Box 14, File 47)
  - “Undergraduate Requirements”, 10/20/1915 (Box 14, File 48)
  - “The Unknown Soldier”, 11/11/1921 (Box 14, File 49)
  - “The Value of College Training”, 5/18/1932 (Box 14, File 50)
  - “Values of Knowledge”, 1/14/1925 (Box 14, File 51)
  - “V. U. History”, 1/16/1934 (Box 14, File 52)
  - “V. U. Library”, undated (Box 14, File 53)
  - “V. U. Problems” At the Southern Colleges Association, 1917 (Box 14, File 54)
  - “Vanderbilt as a College of Liberal Arts”, 9/25/1929 (Box 14, File 55)
  - “Vanderbilt in Retrospect” (1), 1925 (Box 14, File 56)
  - “Vanderbilt in Retrospect” (2), 1925 (Box 14, File 57)
  - “Vanderbilt University in Retrospect” (1) At the Celebration of VU Fiftieth Anniversary, 10/15/1925 (Box 14, File 58)
  - “Vanderbilt University in Retrospect” (2) At the Celebration of VU Fiftieth Anniversary, 10/15/1925 (Box 14, File 59)
  - “World War I”, undated (Box 14, File 60)
  - “Young Man of Future and His Preparation”, undated (Box 14, File 61)
  - Untitled Address of Welcome to the Classical Association, 3/26/1937 (Box 14, File 62)
  - Address of Welcome at a Convention in Nashville, undated (Box 14, File 63)
  - At the Alumni Dinner of Vanderbilt University, 5/27/1915 (Box 14, File 64)
  - At the Alumni Dinner in Nashville, 6/6/1932 (Box 14, File 65)
  - At the Alumni Dinner in Nashville, 6/7/1937 (Box 14, File 66)
  - At the Alumni Dinner in Nashville, undated (Box 14, File 67)
  - At the Alumni Dinner in Nashville, undated (Box 14, File 68)
  - At the Alumni Reunion Dinner, 6/8/1931 (Box 14, File 69)
  - At the American Association for the Advancement of Service, 12/26/1927 (Box 14, File 70)
  - At the Annual Dinner of the Association of American Colleges, 1/8/1925 (Box 14, File 71)
- Writings - Addresses
  - At the Association of American Medical Colleges, 10/29/1934 (Box 15, File 1)
  - At Augusta, Georgia, undated (Box 15, File 2)
  - At Business School of Peace, undated (Box 15, File 3)
  - At Catholic University of America, undated (Box 15, File 4)
  - At the Commencement of Vanderbilt University, 5/29/1913 (Box 15, File 5)
  - At the Commencement in a School, Birmingham, Alabama, undated (Box 15, File 6)
  - At the Demonstration School, Peabody College, 2/19/1925 (Box 15, File 7)
  - At the Dinner in Honor of Dr. G. Canby Robinson, 1/7/1938 (Box 15, File 8)
  - At the Dinner in Honor of John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Mr. Julius Rosenwald, in Nashville, Tennessee, 6/6/1928 (Box 15, File 9)
  - At the Dinner of the Sons of American Revolution Association, 2/22/1921 (Box 15, File 10)
  - At the Exchange Club, undated (Box 15, File 11)
  - At the First Assembly of Students and Faculty, VU, 9/25/1935 (Box 15, File 12)
  - At Fisk University Dinner Held in New York City, 4/25/1933 (Box 15, File 13)
  - At the Fortieth Anniversary as Chancellor of VU, 6/12/1933 (Box 15, File 14)
  - At the Inauguration of Chancellor Brown Boston College, undated (Box 15, File 15)
  - At the Inauguration of Francis P. Gaines as President of Washington and Lee University, 10/25/1930 (Box 15, File 16)
  - At the Inauguration of W. L. Wilson as President of Washington and Lee University, undated (Box 15, File 17)
  - At an Invitation Luncheon, undated (Box 15, File 18)
  - At Louisville, KY, undated (Box 15, File 19)
  - At the Luncheon in Honor of Bishop E. P. Dandridge, 9/20/1938 (Box 15, File 20)
  - At the Luncheon of Workers in the Meharry Campaign, 5/24/1929 (Box 15, File 21)
  - At the Meeting of the Board of Trust, Vanderbilt University, 2/1/1937 (Box 15, File 22)
  - At the Meeting of the Teachers’ Association, undated (Box 15, File 23)
  - At the Meeting of Tennessee College Association, 3/24/1937 (Box 15, File 24)
  - At the Meeting Under the Auspices of Fisk University, 4/13/1937 (Box 15, File 25)
  - At the Memorial Service for Dr. G. B. Winton, 3/23/1938 (Box 15, File 26)
  - At the Memorial Service for France A. White, undated (Box 15, File 27)
  - At the Memorial Service for W. F. Tillett, 11/1/1936 (Box 15, File 28)
  - At the Memorial Service for Senator W. R. Webb, undated (Box 15, File 29)
  - At Randolph-Macon Woman’s College, 3/12/1921 (Box 15, File 30)
  - At Religious Education Association Convention St. Louis, Missouri, 3/12/1912 (Box 15, File 31)
  - At the School of Engineering Smoker, 12/10/1935 (Box 15, File 32)
  - At the Southern Athletic Conference, 12/14/1928 (Box 15, File 33)
  - At the Southern College Association, 11/14/1912 (Box 15, File 34)
  - At the Southern Sociological Congress Atlanta, Georgia, 4/25/1913 (Box 15, File 35)
  - At the Southern University Conference, Louisville, KY, 12/6/1935 (Box 15, File 36)
  - At the Southern University Conference, 11/1/1937 (Box 15, File 37)
  - At the Teachers Association, Bowling Green, KY, 12/1/1916 (Box 15, File 38)
  - At the Tennessee School and College Association, 12/2/1897 (Box 15, File 39)
  - At the Tennessee Society of New York, undated (Box 15, File 40)
  - At the Tennessee Society of St. Louis, 1/8/1917 (Box 15, File 41)
  - At Trinity College, undated (Box 15, File 42)
  - At University of Texas, undated (Box 15, File 43)
  - At Vanderbilt Woman’s Club, 1/19/1934 (Box 15, File 44)
  - At Washington Conference, 5/7/1921 (Box 15, File 45)
  - At Webb School, 3/28/1920 (Box 15, File 46)
  - At Webb School, 2/14/1927 (Box 15, File 47)
  - At Webb School, 3/10/1929 (Box 15, File 48)
  - At West Camp Y.M.C.A., 10/3/1915 (Box 15, File 49)
  - At Y.M.C.A., 2/7/1915 (Box 15, File 50)
  - At Y.M.C.A., 10/14/1917 (Box 15, File 51)
  - At Y.M.C.A. in Memphis, Tennessee, undated (Box 15, File 52)
  - Fragments and Illegibles, undated (Box 15, File 53)
- Writings - Essays
  - “The Advance of Higher Education in the South” Nashville Banner, 1/11/1927 (Box 15, File 54)
  - “American After the War”, undated (Box 15, File 55)
  - “The Apology of Socrates: An Appreciation”, undated (Box 15, File 56)
  - “A Brief History of Vanderbilt University”, undated (Box 15, File 57)
  - “Child Labor”, undated (Box 15, File 58)
  - “College Life and Intellectual Skepticism”, undated (Box 15, File 59)
  - “College Man As A Citizen”, undated (Box 15, File 60)
  - “College Standards -- A Public Interest”, undated (Box 15, File 61)
  - “Conditions of Efficient Faculty Service”, undated (Box 15, File 62)
  - Definition of A College of Liberal Arts”, undated (Box 15, File 63)
- Writings - Essays
  - “Evolution”, 1/27/1923 (Box 16, File 1)
  - “Extra-Curriculum Or Extra-Curricular?”, undated (Box 16, File 2)
  - “Facts About Vanderbilt University School of Medicine and Hospital”, undated (Box 16, File 3)
  - “Financial Problems of Southern Colleges”, undated (Box 16, File 4)
  - “Forward for Charles Barham’s Album”, undated (Box 16, File 5)
  - “Freedom of Speech in the South”, undated (Box 16, File 6)
  - “General Alumni Endowment Fund”, undated (Box 16, File 7)
  - “Going to College”, undated (Box 16, File 8)
  - “The High School and the University”, undated (Box 16, File 9)
  - “Higher Education and Economic Development”, undated (Box 16, File 10)
  - “Higher Education in the South”, undated (Box 16, File 11)
  - “Higher Education in the South, 1875-1925”, undated (Box 16, File 12)
  - “The Intellectual Tendencies of the South”, undated (Box 16, File 13)
  - “Life and Teaching of Charles Darwin”, 3/1928 (Box 16, File 14)
  - “The National Significance of the Life and Work of Mr. Robert C. Ogden”, undated (Box 16, File 15)
  - “Notes on the History of Vanderbilt University During the Last Fifty years”, 1/7/1925 (Box 16, File 16)
  - “Obligations of American Life”, undated (Box 16, File 17)
  - “Patriotism and Educational Service”, undated (Box 16, File 18)
  - “Problems of Reconstruction”, undated (Box 16, File 19)
  - “Progress in Higher Education Since 1787”, undated (Box 16, File 20)
  - “The Relations of Education to Economic Development” (Box 16, File 21)
  - “Review of the Decision of the Vanderbilt Commission”, undated (Box 16, File 22)
  - “The Service of Citizenship”, undated (Box 16, File 23)
  - “The Service of Citizenship” (revised), undated (Box 16, File 24)
  - “Sketch of Vanderbilt University prepared for the Use of School”, [1926] (Box 16, File 25)
  - “The Soul of America”, undated (Box 16, File 26)
  - “The Spirit of the University”, undated (Box 16, File 27)
  - “Support of Higher Education by State”, undated (Box 16, File 28)
  - Untitled (1) – [on Education], undated (Box 16, File 29)
  - Untitled (2) – [on Education], undated (Box 16, File 30)
- Writings - Lectures
  - “American Ideals”, undated (Box 16, File 31)
  - “Andrew Jackson As Example”, undated (Box 16, File 32)
  - “Assyria”, undated (Box 16, File 33)
  - “Athletics”, undated (Box 16, File 34)
  - “Baghdad Ry”, undated (Box 16, File 35)
  - “The Book of Job” (Part 1), undated (Box 16, File 36)
  - “The Book of Job” (Part 2), undated (Box 16, File 37)
  - “The Book of Job” (Part 3), undated (Box 16, File 38)
  - “British Empire and Imperial Federation”, 1/31/1914 (Box 16, File 39)
  - “Burbank”, undated (Box 16, File 40)
  - “College Freedom”, undated (Box 16, File 41)
  - “Constantinople”, undated (Box 16, File 42)
  - “Czech-Slovak”, undated (Box 16, File 43)
- Writings - Lectures
  - “Education”, undated (Box 17, File 1)
  - “Fraternities”, undated (Box 17, File 2)
  - “Germany, a World Power”, 3/22/1913 (Box 17, File 3)
  - “Greece - Crete - Venizelos”, undated (Box 17, File 4)
  - “Holland”, undated (Box 17, File 5)
  - “History of War”, undated (Box 17, File 6)
  - “How Germany Is Governed”, 3/2/1918 (Box 17, File 7)
  - “Julius Caesar”, undated (Box 17, File 8)
  - “Portugal”, undated (Box 17, File 9)
  - “The Present Crisis”, undated (Box 17, File 10)
  - “Rabbi Lewinthal”, undated (Box 17, File 11)
  - “Reigns of the Kings of England”, undated (Box 17, File 12)
  - “Ruskin”, 4/21/1900 (Box 17, File 13)
  - “Shelley”, undated (Box 17, File 14)
  - “Shelley’s Poetry”, 10/1887 (Box 17, File 15)
  - “Tennyson”, undated (Box 17, File 16)
- Writings - Sermons
  - At Vanderbilt University Chapel, 2/16/1916 (Box 17, File 17)
  - “Bible”, undated (Box 17, File 18)
  - “Hollowed Thy Name”, undated (Box 17, File 19)
  - “Thy Kingdom Come”, undated (Box 17, File 20)
  - “The Kingdom of God”, undated (Box 17, File 21)
  - “Opening Chapel Address, Vanderbilt University”, 9/28/1927 (Box 17, File 22)
  - “Thy Will Be Done”, undated (Box 17, File 23)
- Writings - Poems
  - “The Great Man”, undated (Box 17, File 24)
  - “The Lay of the Last Minstrel”, undated (Box 17, File 25)
  - “Silver Jack”, undated (Box 17, File 26)
  - “Telegraph to Theodore”, undated (Box 17, File 27)
  - Untitled (1), undated (Box 17, File 28)
  - Untitled (2), undated (Box 17, File 29)
- Writings - Reports
  - To the Board of Trust of Vanderbilt University Annual Meeting, 1894 (Box 17, File 30)
  - To the Board of Trust of Vanderbilt University Annual Meeting, 1895 (Box 17, File 31)
  - To the Board of Trust of Vanderbilt University Annual Meeting, 1896 (Box 17, File 32)
  - To the Board of Trust of Vanderbilt University Annual Meeting, 1897 (Box 17, File 33)
  - To the Board of Trust of Vanderbilt University Annual Meeting, 1898 (Box 17, File 34)
  - To the Board of Trust of Vanderbilt University Annual Meeting, 1899 (Box 17, File 35)
  - To the Board of Trust of Vanderbilt University Annual Meeting, 1902 (Box 17, File 36)
  - To the Faculty and Alumni of Vanderbilt University, 1937 (Box 17, File 37)
- Writings - Book Manuscripts
  - History of Vanderbilt University Book I: Introduction and Chapter 1 (Box 17, File 38)
  - Chapter 2 (Box 17, File 39)
  - Chapter 3 and Chapter 4 (Box 17, File 40)
  - Chapter 5 (Box 17, File 41)
  - Chapter 6 (Box 17, File 42)
  - Chapter 7 (Box 17, File 43)
  - Chapter 8 and Chapter 9 (Box 17, File 44)
  - Book II: Chapter 1 and Chapter 2 (Box 17, File 45)
  - Chapter 3 and Chapter 4 (Box 17, File 46)
  - Chapter 5 and Chapter 6 (Box 17, File 47)
  - Book III: Chapter 1 (Box 17, File 48)
  - Chapter 2 (Box 17, File 49)
  - Chapter 3 (Box 17, File 50)
- Writings - Published Articles
  - “Address At the Reunion Dinner”, 6/8/1931 (Box 17, File 51)
  - “Address at Inauguration of President McKenzie, Fisk University”, undated (Box 17, File 52)
  - “Address at the Chapel”, undated (Box 17, File 53)
  - “Address to the Alumni and Former Students of Vanderbilt University”, undated (Box 17, File 54)
  - “America and the Present Crisis”, 3/28/1917 (Box 17, File 55)
  - “Chancellor Kirkland’s Opening Address” The Vanderbilt Alumnus, 10/1927 (Box 17, File 56)
  - “College Ideals” Alumni Bulletin of the University of Virginia v15 n4, 10/1922 (Box 17, File 57)
  - “College Standards -- A Public Interest” Proceedings of the 14th Annual Meeting of the Southern Association of College Women, undated (Box 17, File 58)
  - “The Duty of the State Toward Higher Education” Delivered before the Southern Educational Association in Memphis, Tennessee, 12/1899 (Box 17, File 59)
- Writings - Published Articles
  - “Extra-Curriculum or Extra-Curricular” The Educational Record v8 n2, 4/1927 (Box 18, File 1)
  - “Forget Me and Think Only of the University” Vanderbilt Alumnus, 6/12/1933 (Box 18, File 2)
  - “Forward”, 2/13/1936 (Box 18, File 3)
  - “German Vs. American Universities” The Monteaglean v1 n5, 8/8/1887 (Box 18, File 4)
  - “Higher Education in the South” Auburn Alumnus, 5/1929 (Box 18, File 5)
  - “Higher Education in the U.S.A.” Vanderbilt University Quarterly, 1913 (Box 18, File 6)
  - “History of Medical Education at Vanderbilt University School of Medicine” Journal of the Association of American Medical Colleges, 1/1935 (Box 18, File 7)
  - “Ideals in the Educational Equation” The Sooner Magazine, 7/1929 (Box 18, File 8)
  - “Inauguration Address at Vanderbilt University”, 9/25/1893 (Box 18, File 9)
  - “Objectives of Standardization of Higher Institutions”, undated (Box 18, File 10)
  - “Obligations of American Life” 1902 Baccalaureate Address, Published by University of the South (Box 18, File 11)
  - “Opening Address at Vanderbilt University” Vanderbilt Observer, 1894 (Box 18, File 12)
  - “An Open Letter”, 3/1922 (Box 18, File 13)
  - “An Open Letter to the Alumni and Former Students of V.U.”, 7/18/1899 (Box 18, File 14)
  - “A Passage in the Anglo-Saxon Poem: ‘The Ruin’ Critically Discussed” American Journal of Philosophy, undated (Box 18, File 15)
  - “Pay Tribute to Philanthropists” Vanderbilt Alumnus, 6/1928 (Box 18, File 16)
  - “The Permanence of Scholastic Ideals” The University Record, 4/1931 (Box 18, File 17)
  - “Personal Touch in Education” The Red Book Magazine v39, 9/1922 (Box 18, File 18)
  - “The Problem of the Future” Vanderbilt Alumnus, 6/1928 (Box 18, File 19)
  - “Progress in Religious and Moral Education” Religious Education, 4/1910 (Box 18, File 20)
  - “Recent History of Vanderbilt University” Methodist Review, 4/1910 (Box 18, File 21)
  - “Remarks of Chancellor Kirkland at the Alumni Dinner” Vanderbilt Alumnus, 1/1936 (Box 18, File 22)
  - “Remarks of Chancellor J.H. Kirkland at a Meeting Held April 13, 1937 in the War Memorial Auditorium, 4/13/1937 (Box 18, File 23)
  - “Report of the Committee on College Standards” The Educational Record v3, 7/1922 (Box 18, File 24)
  - “Report of the Committee on Program of Studies for Preparatory Schools” Proceedings of the Association of Colleges and Preparatory Schools of the Southern States, undated (Box 18, File 25)
- Writings - Published Articles
  - “Report to the Board of Trust of Vanderbilt University”, 1936 (Box 19, File 1)
  - “Report to the Ladies’ Aid Society at Vanderbilt University”, 1901 (Box 19, File 2)
  - “The School as a Force Arrayed Against Child Labor”, 1905 (Box 19, File 3)
  - “Should Endowed College Be Taxed for Serving the Public?”, Undated (Box 19, File 4)
  - “Some Errors in Harper’s Latin Dictionary” (Box 19, File 5)
  - “Statement for the Vanderbilt Commission”, 1906 (Box 19, File 6)
  - “A Study of the Anglo-Saxon Poem, the Harrowing of Hell”, 1885 (Box 19, File 7)
  - “Suggestion for Future Work”, 1907 (Box 19, File 8)
  - “To the Alumni of Vanderbilt University”, 1926 (Box 19, File 9)
  - “Vanderbilt to Sewanee”, 1907 (Box 19, File 10)
  - “Vanderbilt University”, 1898 (Box 19, File 11)
  - “Vanderbilt University and Preparatory Classes”, 1896 (Box 19, File 12)
  - “What It Is To Be A College President”, 1909 (Box 19, File 13)
- Personal/Biographical Material
  - Biographical Information (Box 19, File 14)
  - Celebrating the 40th Year of Service of J.H. Kirkland (1) (Box 19, File 15)